And I have to plug it through on
the radio.
I think it's like,
it's like my first password
basically.
Like I did submit yesterday,
but like that was just to see
how bad the form was.
Which is bad,
but like I did submit here.
After my last class,
I'm gonna like submit again, and
then we'll see.
I got you,
yeah,
well.
Just past 1030 so we'll get
started, get to see everyone
again.
Announcements,
so homework three is due on
Friday.
There's a survey at the very
beginning of the homework that
asks you about your experience
in the class so far, but
importantly don't fill it out
until you've done the rest of
the homework because one of the
things it asks for is how much
time did you spend on homeworks
one, two, and three,
so I want you to finish homework
three before doing that.
I look at the responses very
closely.
So please provide honest
feedback.
And if there are changes we can
make to improve your experience
that are in line with our
learning goals, we're happy to
do that.
Another thing I notified you
about last night is that if you
go on pensive, there's now an
assignment called the grade
report, where you can see a
report card for you in this
class.
It shows you your scores on
homework so far,
combining your auto grader and
written scores for homeworks one
and two.
It shows you all the lectures I
have your attendance for it
shows all the labs you have
attended
It shows the slip days you've
used on homework.
So it has everything I know
about you in this class so far
So make sure to take a look at
that.
And if something doesn't seem
right, let me know because
that's what I'm going to use
ultimately
To compute your grades at the
end of the semester and it
doesn't update automatically.
Okay, so like when
Like after today's lecture It's
not going to automatically say
that you came to lecture today
Like it's a manual process to
update it and I'll probably do
that every week or every other
week So at the top of it, it
says very clearly when it was
last updated.
So it should say yesterday or
today
And yeah, if there are any
issues with it, let me know and
I can fix it and we can take a
look
Couple other things we added a
few more evening office hours I
think students either mentioned
in the survey or last week in
lab that it would be nice to
have more office hours after 3
o'clock so some of the TAs added
evening office hours and I will
try and add some as well.
In fact I'm gonna do central
campus office hours today for my
other class so I'll put that on
the calendar for you guys as
well.
And then lastly make sure to
keep up with assignment
solutions.
Homework 2 solutions have been
released and in general homework
solutions will come out two days
like three days after the
homework is due because again
people could use two slip days
on it so we have to wait until
that The deadline is over.
OK,
the plan for today is to start
by recapping the big ideas from
Thursday's class, which is the
big, big idea was that of the
dot product, which is an
operation that involves two
vectors and returns a scalar.
And what we tried to understand
on Thursday is,
what is the meaning of that
scalar? And in doing that,
we looked at two equivalent
definitions of the dot product,
and the fact that they're
equivalent tells us something
about the meaning of the dot
product.
Sort of as a tangent, I will
introduce two important
inequalities that we use a lot
in machine learning that involve
the lengths of vectors.
And then the new big idea for
today is what I'll call the
approximation problem, which is
how we best approximate one
vector using another.
And the solution is what we will
call orthogonal projections.
projections
Okay,
let's start by recapping
Let's suppose we have two
vectors
u and v
What was the first definition of
the dot product I gave you
Yeah.
Got it.
Like u1 times v1 plus u2 times
v2.
Good.
So the precursor here is that we
need to start by assuming these
vectors u and v have the same
number of components.
And what they do, their dot
product comes from multiplying
the first component in u with
the first component in v.
That's u1, v1,
plus the second component in u
times the second component in v,
plus all the way through the
last component in u times the
last component in v.
This is what I'll sometimes call
the algebraic or computational
definition.
But that definition,
or I shouldn't say that.
I should say there's also
another definition of the dot
product.
And we proved that these two
definitions were equal last
Thursday.
What was the other definition
that we discovered on Thursday?
Zara?
magnitude times the cosine
between them.
Good, it was the length of u
times the length of v
cosine theta,
where theta is the angle
between u
and v.
Now, if we look at two vectors
in R2 or two vectors in R3,
we can visualize what the angle
between them is.
What does it mean for there to
be an angle between two vectors
in R17?
We can't visualize,
right?
This is some high dimensional
thinking.
So it's not clear geometrically
to us what the angle should be,
but this definition of the dot
product tells us what the angle
between any two vectors is, even
if we can't visualize them.
OK, so we can use this as a way
of defining what the angle
between two vectors is,
even if it doesn't make
geometric sense to us.
And like we said,
I want to be clear here,
these are always equal.
So it's not like sometimes you
use one dot product, sometimes
you use another.
No, these always give you the
same result for any two vectors,
and we derived that last class.
Okay, so the fact that the dot
product
between u and v can be computed
in this geometric definition,
the length of u times the length
of v cos theta, like I just
said, allows you to define what
the angle between u and v is.
And one way you can do that is
by taking this first equation
and dividing both sides by the
length of u and the length of v.
And that gives you that the cos
of the angle between u and v
is the dot product over the
product of the length.
And the dot product,
we have two ways of calculating
it.
One is the geometric way, but
the more usual way you will
actually calculate it is using
the algebraic way from the last
slide,
where you have u1 v1 plus u2 v2
and so on.
So if you have the list of
numbers for u, the list of
numbers for v,
you can find the numerator and
denominator.
And what this gives you is a way
of finding the cosine of the
angle between them.
And this quantity here,
what was the term we used for
this last class?
u dot v over the length of u
times the length of v.
There is a name for that.
Alex.
Good, it's what we'll call the
cosine similarity.
So anytime you see a cos theta,
that's referring to cosine
similarity.
Now remind me what the range of
possible values for cosine
similarity is.
Just stop.
Negative 1 to 1.
Yeah.
The cosine of a theta is at most
1,
and at the lowest it could be is
negative 1.
How do you get a cosine theta of
1?
What two vectors would have a
cosine similarity of positive 1?
How would they have to be
oriented? Good.
Yeah?
Vectors that are scalar
multiples.
Good.
Vectors that point in the same
direction.
Notice that's slightly different
than them being scalar
multiples, because what about
this vector and this vector?
They're scalar multiples of each
other.
Pretend I have origin here.
But they don't point in the same
direction.
They point in opposite
directions.
But you have the right idea.
So here, I'll say u and v point
in the same direction.
And for negative 1,
we'll say u and v point in
opposite
directions.
What's the case exactly in the
middle?
Yeah,
yeah.
When the cosine of theta is 0,
that means theta itself
is 90 degrees,
OK?
Because cos theta,
let's say, cos 90 equals 0.
And we say U and V are
perpendicular slash
orthogonal.
Which means if you draw them,
they'll look something like
this.
Now, again,
you may say, well, what does it
mean for two vectors in R17 to
be orthogonal? What does a
90-degree angle in 17 dimensions
look like? I don't know.
But we will use this as the
definition for what it means for
vectors to be orthogonal in 17
dimensions, or whatever
dimensions we want.
Yeah, Paul.
Is there like an intuition for
why cosine of theta being 1
means it's the same direction?
It's because I can add as
another slide here.
When cosine theta is 1,
that means theta itself is 0
degrees.
That means the angle between the
vectors is 0.
So if this is v u would have to
be something like this.
Okay.
Thank you.
Yeah good
Okay, so are you comfortable for
what you with what it means for
vectors to be orthogonal
Okay,
their dot product is zero.
It means the angle between them
is 90 degrees now.
We don't always
You know like the fact that the
angle between them is 90 degrees
Like I said when the vectors
have lots and lots of components
in them that's not necessarily a
geometric fact we care about
rather we use this as a proxy to
mean these vectors are sort of
Unrelated or are as different as
can be they point in very
different directions
Right pointing in different
directions is a little confusing
of an idea because okay pretend
this is you This is V these
point in total opposite
directions, but they lie on the
same line So there's like
something similar about them,
right?
Whereas these two vectors
truly point in, well I guess the
term is, orthogonal directions.
They're moving in totally
different directions.
So like these two vectors are
different and these two vectors
are different, but the way in
which they are different is not
the same.
And so like I said at the end of
Thursday's class, this idea of
orthogonality is one that is
going to come up quite a bit
including in the new idea that
we talked about today.
But this idea of cosine
similarity is one that has lots
of practical use cases.
And in either this week's lab or
this week's homework, you're
going to,
I think I told you about the
presidential speeches example,
where you're going to take
speeches, convert them to
vectors, and use that to figure
out what are the most similar
speeches and what are the least
similar speeches by US
presidents.
And you can use the same idea to
quantify how similar or
different any documents are.
So this is a very practically
used idea.
Questions with cosine
similarity?
And the dot product more
generally
Okay,
one thing I'll say is if we come
to the course website
And we take a look at your
current homework There are
several properties of the dot
product that you're gonna have
to look at the notes to sort of
figure out some of these we
reviewed when doing the like
derivation of the cosine version
of the dot product formula.
But question five on homework
three, for example,
has you used the distributive
property of the dot product to
figure out, OK, well, 3u minus
4v's dot product with u plus 9v
is some random number.
What is the dot product of u and
v?
So to figure that out, you have
to use the distributive
property, and you look at the
notes for that.
That's just something I wanted
to flag.
OK,
like I said, as an aside,
there are two important
inequalities that come up a lot
in machine learning adjacent
proofs.
And so I want to state them
clearly here, though this is all
still in chapter 3.3
of the notes.
Two important inequalities.
Now, both of them,
I mean, they have names that
maybe you haven't heard of
before.
But what they tell you is maybe
a little more intuitive than
they sound.
OK.
So let's use this right here.
What is the biggest possible
dot? OK, let's put it this way.
Let's pretend u has a length of
5 and v has a length of 10.
What is the biggest possible
value of their dot product?
All I'm telling you is u has a
length of 5, v has a length of
10.
What is the biggest their dot
product could be?
50.
How did you think of that?
Because the biggest cosine could
be it's 1.
So 5 times 10 is 50.
And then cosine,
if it's at its max, it'd be 1.
Exactly.
All I'm telling you is that, OK,
we got one vector that has a
length of 5.
Make my arm half alike.
And one that has a length of 10.
And your job is to make their
dot product as big as possible.
Well, what you would do is make
them a line.
Because we know that the smaller
the angle between them is, the
bigger their dot product is.
And if you want their dot
product to be 0, Oh, then, well,
OK, put them at a 90-degree
angle.
So the biggest their dot product
could be is the product of their
lengths.
What's the smallest their dot
product could be?
Including negative values.
We know it could be 0.
What's the smallest it could be?
If u has a length of 5, u has a
length of 10.
Yeah,
generally.
Negative 50, right? You can make
them point in opposite
directions.
So all this is really telling
you is what the biggest and
smallest possible dot products
between two vectors are.
And this inequality I'm about to
write There's just a fancy way
of stating that Yeah, the reason
I gave you this like Preface is
because the name of the
inequality sounds like it's some
crazy fancy stuff.
Kaoshi-Schwarz inequality
But all it says is literally the
demonstration we just did which
is that the dot product
In absolute value
Can't be more than the product
of the links
Notice on the left,
those vertical bars, those are
absolute value bars, because u
dot v is a number.
You don't take the magnitude,
you don't use the double bars
for a number, that's for a
vector.
So this is the absolute value of
the dot product,
has to be less than or equal to
the product of the length.
Why do we have the absolute
value there?
Well,
think about the example we just
worked through, where the
biggest dot product could be 50,
and the smallest could be
negative 50.
All this is saying is that in
terms of its size, the dot
product has to be less than 50,
less than or equal to 50.
You can't make it output a
bigger number than 50.
Are we clear on where that comes
from?
OK, I'm going to have you work
on an activity that involves the
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality in
just a bit.
The second is called the
triangle inequality.
This one,
its definition doesn't directly
involve the dot product, though
if you take a look at the notes
in chapter 3.3,
the way we prove it involves the
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality.
And more details in 3.3.
If you had to guess, what do you
think the triangle inequality
says?
Or maybe think back to high
school geometry.
There is a rule that no matter
what triangle you cook up,
there's like a rule that the
triangle had to follow,
something about its side
lengths.
Sorry.
The sum of two sides is greater
than this.
Yeah, exactly.
It's saying, if you take any two
sides and add up their lengths,
it has to be bigger than the
length of the third side.
Or in other words,
no side in a triangle can be
longer than the sum of the other
two.
OK.
That's all the triangle
inequality says.
It's just that the vectors
involved, suppose this is v and
this is u,
And the triangle inequality says
something about u,
v, and their sum,
u plus v,
which sort of define a triangle
if you think about how we did
tip-to-tail addition when we
first introduced vectors a week
ago.
So all this is saying here is
that the length of u plus v
is less than the length of u
plus the length of v.
But actually,
that would be true if this were
a direct parallel of the
geometric triangle inequality we
just talked about.
But I'm going to add a less than
or equal to,
because there are several cases
where it could be equal to.
Because u,
v, and their sum don't
necessarily need to form a
triangle.
Can you give me an example where
this inequality would be an
equality,
where the length of u plus v
would be exactly the length of u
plus the length of v, whole n?
When they are at the same
directions?
Yeah, what if they point in the
same direction? Or what if
they're just the same vector?
What if u is 1, 1 and v is 1,
1?
Well, then on both sides,
this should be computing the
length of the vector 2,
2.
But in general, if they point in
the same direction,
then yeah, u, v, and u plus v
don't make a triangle.
Because u plus v lives on the
same line that u and v live on.
As another example, what if v is
the 0 vector?
It's the vector of zeros.
Okay, then on both sides we have
the length of u
All right, but in general all
this is saying is that no side
of a triangle can be longer than
the sum of the other two sides
Okay
The utility in defining these
things is that we can use them
even when the vectors live in
dimensions that we can't
visualize Okay, so this is true
even in that for vectors in r17.
There's nothing special about
the number 17 I just use it
because it's a random sounding
number that doesn't seem like it
has any special properties about
it
Okay, here's an activity I want
you to work on,
and this is like a very classic
245 midterm one question.
So let me restate for you that
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality,
it says that if u and v are
vectors implicitly this requires
that they have the same number
of components because otherwise
you can't take the dot product.
The absolute value of their dot
product is less than or equal to
the length of the first times
the length of the second.
Prove that for any positive
numbers a and b,
a plus b over 2
is greater than or equal to
the square root of a times b.
Now you may say, wait, hold up.
Something's confusing here,
because the Cauchy-Schwarz
inequality is about vectors.
But now I've asked you to prove
something It has nothing to do
with vectors.
It has something to do with
these two positive numbers.
By the way,
this quantity on the right is
the regular average of a and b,
or we may call this the
arithmetic mean.
What is the thing on the left?
Yeah.
It's the geometric mean.
This is sometimes in math called
the AM-GM inequality.
It means the arithmetic mean is
always greater than or equal to
the geometric mean.
And what I want you to do is
prove that just for the case
where you have two numbers, but
it's true no matter how many
numbers you have.
And again, this is sort of an
aside, but the harmonic mean,
which you saw in the first two
labs,
also can be tacked on here.
That's less than or equal to
this as well.
That would be 2 over 1 over a
plus 1 over b.
We'll leave that aside for now.
Back to the confusing part here,
I've asked you to prove
something that has nothing to do
with vectors, but there's an
inequality,
right?
And here's the general strategy
to questions like this.
What you have to do, and this is
like a creative thinking
question,
is think of vectors u and v,
such that if you plug them into
the Cauchy-Schwarz inequality,
they tell you something about
the thing you're trying to do.
That is, you have to think of
vectors u and v
in which you creatively arrange
where the a's and b's are,
such that if you take u and v,
plug them into the
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality, which
is always true no matter what
vectors you think of,
then
what comes out of that
inequality is the inequality
that you're trying to prove,
or a version that you can
rearrange to get to them.
So I'll give you a couple hints.
Both vectors have two
components.
And there are a few ways you can
do this.
But the easiest way to think
about it, I think, is put an A
there.
Now what I want you to
experiment with is, what else
would you put in the other
spots?
And if you plug that into the
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality, what
would come out.
So experiment a little,
and we'll go from there.
And this should be sort of like
a group activity,
like discuss with the people
near you.
What do you try? You try one
thing, I try another thing.
Yeah.
A, B, B,
A.
A, B, B, A.
A, B,
A.
A, B, B, A.
A, B, B,
A.
A, B, B, A.
A, B, B,
A.
A, B, B, A.
A,
B,
A.
That's the problem.
We've got a b plus a b equals
the cosine squared plus a
b.
I realize I gave you a
misleading hint.
It's not supposed to be a here.
And if you started playing
around with this, you'll see why
that doesn't work.
Because somewhere you'll end up
with an a squared, which doesn't
appear here.
What's the solution?
Square root the a.
You can put whatever you want.
now this is more trivial.
It's gonna be.
So, where is the area?
Okay, so I'm gonna try.
Wherever you play,
zero.
Zero.
We're starting here.
It's okay.
No,
wait,
doesn't that work for you? Screw
it in, screw it in, screw it in,
screw it in, screw it in, screw
it in,
screw it in, screw it in.
No,
no,
no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no,
no, no, no.
Yeah, that's what I did.
It's kind of impressive.
Wait,
yeah, so we get to take back
into the U square, U square,
U square, U square,
U square,
U square, U square, U square, U
square, U square, U square, U
square, experiment a little and
then we can discuss some
approaches.
Okay, let's recall what the
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality says,
and I'll keep that at the top,
which says that the absolute
value of the dot product of u
and v for whichever u and v we
think of is less than the
product of the links.
Now the initial hint I gave you,
which was the wrong hint to
give,
said that let's Let's pretend U
had A as its first
component.
When you started experimenting
with that, how else did you fill
out U and V?
What did you try?
You tried A, B, and B, A.
Sure.
Why didn't you try A, B, and A,
B?
It didn't feel right.
OK.
OK,
let's see what would happen if
we tried a, b, a, b.
What would the left side of the
inequality tell us?
Let me write this out in good
form.
u dot v's absolute value is less
than or equal to length of u
times the length of v.
What do we have on the left?
I have the absolute value of the
dot product of u and v.
What is that?
Yeah.
I would have a squared plus b
squared,
right?
If what I did was have ab and
ab,
right?
I would give a times a plus b
times b.
That would be what I would have
on the left.
And on the right, what would I
have?
What's the length of u?
It's the square root of the sum
of the squares of its
components.
And what are those components?
a and b, so it should be the
square root of a squared plus b
squared.
But since here, in this
hypothetical example, I made v
be the same vector,
its length would also be the
same thing.
So I could just square this
whole thing.
But then when you realize that I
told you that a and b had to be
non-negative,
even if they weren't
this can't be negative, a
squared plus b squared.
So then when the absolute values
drop,
all this tells you is that a
squared plus b squared is less
than or equal to a squared plus
b squared.
Which is not super insightful.
We knew that already.
So that's a first hint when
dealing with these
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality
questions.
It's almost never the case that
the u and v are supposed to be
the same.
You're supposed to arrange them
in a way that when you take the
dot product of the two, that
gives you something different
than just multiplying the
lengths independently.
So what's the next thing you
might try? Well,
as was hinted,
maybe we try v being ba.
What does that give us?
Now on the left-hand side,
what do I get?
I have the absolute value of
what?
If u is ab and v is ba, what do
I have on the left-hand side?
2 times ab, good.
And I can drop the absolute
value, Because again, I know
here,
I told you that both A and B are
not negative.
And on the right, what do I
have?
Well,
u is the same as before.
Its length is the square root of
a squared plus b squared.
And here, all I did was shuffle
the elements in v
so it doesn't change its length.
So really,
that is still being squared.
So this almost looks like what I
want.
If I write this again,
I have 2ab is less than or equal
to a squared plus b squared,
which means ab is less than or
equal to a squared plus b
squared over 2.
This is like similar-ish to the
thing I told you to prove.
But everything in the thing I
told you to prove is a square
root of these variables, right?
On the left,
we have an ab here,
but we wanted a square root of
ab.
And on the right,
we have an a squared plus b
squared on the numerator, but
you wanted just an a plus b.
So what's the solution?
Just square root everything in
the vector that we define.
We defined u and v.
We can do that however we'd
like.
So if we define u and v to be
root a root b
and v to be root b root a,
then the Cauchy-Schwarz
inequality tells us well the
absolute value of their dot
product is less than or equal to
the product of their lengths.
What do we have on the left?
I have the absolute value of
what?
Guess you want to remind me.
Good,
because I have square root of a
times square root of b plus
square root of b times the
square root of a.
That just looks like 2 times the
square root of AB.
Again, that can't be negative,
so I'll drop the absolute value.
On the left, what do I have?
Well, what's the length of u?
It's the square root of the
square root of A squared
plus the square root of B
squared.
And then the length of V is also
the same thing.
So if we really want to write
this out thoroughly,
say something like this.
On the left,
I still have my square,
2 times the square root of AB,
and on the right, what do I
have?
Well, these two things are the
same, so I can keep one of them
and drop the square root.
And then, what's the square root
of A?
Squared?
Well, that's just A.
And what's the square root of B?
Squared, that's just B.
So on the left,
I have the square root of A plus
B squared,
so this tells me 2 times the
square root of AB is just less
than or equal to A plus B, which
is exactly the thing I told you
to prove,
if you divide both sides by 2.
So I think this is kind of
interesting.
This inequality has nothing to
do with vectors, yet we were
able to use just properties of
the dot product and an
inequality we defined with that
to prove seemingly unrelated
things.
So this Cauchy-Schwarz
inequality comes up a lot.
And like I said,
a common midterm one question in
the past,
I don't know if it'll the future
midterm one question, haven't
wrote it yet,
has been use the Cauchy-Schwarz
inequality to prove some other
fact about numbers provided in
the question.
Questions with questions like
this.
And I guess one thing I'll say
here is that there's no way I
was really expecting you to be
able to know that this is how
you were supposed to use the
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality to
arrive here.
There's no way you would know
how to do this before this.
As you practice more and more of
these, now that you have this
example in your toolkit,
you are way better equipped to
see a new question that asks
something like this.
And you're better equipped to be
able to make informed guesses as
to what to put in u and v.
And what I hopefully tried to
illustrate is that you're not
supposed to just look at it and
know what u and v are supposed
to be.
You try some things, it doesn't
work, and then you use that to
update your guess and use that
to arrive at a solution.
Can we get partial credit for
identifying that we would have
to use Cauchy-Schwartz here?
Usually in a question like this,
we will say, so use the
Cauchy-Schwartz inequality to do
that.
Yeah,
good question.
Other questions with that?
But I guess what I'll say to
that is,
there are only so many patterns
that this can follow.
And if you look at the past
midterm one questions, and this
is all on the course website,
But if you click the Resources
tab and go to Exams,
we can do that here.
You go to Resources,
click Past Exams here.
You can see all of the past
midterm ones.
And some of the finals will have
questions about this as well.
And in fact, if you click the
Vectors topic
and just search for
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality,
you'll find a bunch of those
questions here.
So this is one that uses the
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality.
Actually, I recorded a video
walkthrough for that.
There are several others if you
scroll through here about the
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality.
Okay, so there's lots of
practice, and if you look at all
of those, it'll help with
identifying the pattern.
Sound okay?
All right.
Okay, before we move on to the
next big idea, let's just take a
short break and do attendance
here.
We'll start at 11.08.
I think that's where it's going
to lead us,
if possible.
OK.
Can you even read it for the
operator?
Ah.
OK.
I have a branch on the docs
right now, what's the website,
is it a platform or a web
browser?
Oh wow, that update is fast.
Everyone checked in?
I'm trying to figure out the
study abroad stuff.
I rebooted my computer and then
only ran these commands at every
time
I
had a time
All right, I'm gonna close the
form
Good.
OK, we're moving to what's now
in chapter 3.4,
which this problem I'm going to
propose at first seems like it
has nothing to do with what we
were just discussing, but as we
will soon see,
they're closely related.
How I'll introduce this is by
calling it the approximation
problem.
And here's how I want you to
think about it.
Pretend I have two vectors, u
and v.
As usual, I've drawn them as
being in R2, but it could be in
any universe,
as long as they both have the
same number of components.
Here u and v don't point in the
same direction.
Here is the question, and this
is really what we're going to
answer for the rest of today.
Among all vectors that point in
the same direction as v,
that is among all scalar
multiples of v,
which one is closest to u?
Okay, what are some of the
scalar multiples of v?
Well, this is a scalar multiple
of v,
this is a scalar multiple of v,
This is a scalar multiple of v.
Those are all scalar multiples
of v.
So are these.
I could look in the opposite way
if I needed to.
Now, for all of these,
the relative angle between u and
that scalar multiple is not
changing.
That angle only has two
possibilities.
Either it's theta if I'm
multiplying v by a positive
number, or it's 180 minus theta
if I'm multiplying v by a
negative number.
Okay,
so the question I'm asking here
is not one that is directly
related to the angle.
I'm not asking which of the
scalar multiples are closest in
terms of cosine similarity.
Instead I'm asking something
that feels a little different.
Let me clearly write what I'm
saying.
among all scalar
multiples of v,
which is closest to u.
Now,
we need to make the problem of
doing this, or problem of
finding the scalar multiple that
is closest to you, a little more
precise.
So why don't we just define a
variable
that corresponds to the amount
we are going to multiply v by?
So let's call that variable k,
and we'll use this for the rest
of the lecture.
And so the real question is,
which k makes kv,
which is a scalar multiple of v
in which I multiplied v by k,
as close to u as possible?
Now,
if we're not asking a question
of the direction, because you
and Kv always live on the same
line, so we're not really asking
which of those is more closely
aligned with you,
how else could I measure how
close Kv is to you?
If not with the angle between
them, what else could I do?
Yeah, sorry.
What's the perpendicular
distance between them?
Well, we'll get to something
about perpendicularity in a
second.
But what if I'm just talking
about u and v? I think you have
the right idea.
How do I measure how far apart u
and v are?
Sure, I could find the angle
between them.
That's one way.
But what's another way I could
find how far apart u and v are?
Right.
Any difference?
Yeah, I could just find sort of
using
the length of the vector between
them,
u minus v.
I could subtract the two.
That'll tell me how to go from v
to u, or if I do it the opposite
way, from u to v.
And I can see how long that
vector is.
Do we agree?
So the idea is, why do we
calculate the difference?
This is the vector u minus v.
And remember, we talked about
how you would determine that
this is the order before.
v plus this vector cancels out
the v we already had and gives
us a u, which is what the end
result is.
And I shouldn't write u minus v.
I should really write u minus
kv.
And the question is, well, what
k makes this vector?
What do we want to do with this
vector that I've drawn and read?
Minimizing?
Yeah, we want to make it as
short as possible.
Let me draw this for a different
kit.
So, to give us a better sense of
the situation here, let's go to
the course notes,
in which we have a little slider
for this.
I'll let that load.
By the way,
over the weekend, I vibe-coded
some extra features here.
Like, you can change the color
of the notes to darker,
and you can change the font.
So if you think of other ideas
that seemed like it would be
easy for my codecs to implement
here, let me know.
Anyways,
same situation,
just the vectors point in
different directions than in my
example.
Imagine the orange vector is U,
blue vector is V.
And the slider changes how much
of v I'm taking.
So it changes the value of k.
So if I have a negative value of
k, it's pointing in the opposite
direction of v.
If I have a positive value of k,
it's pointing in the direction
of v.
So the question is, among all of
these vectors,
which one's difference with u is
as short as possible?
To maybe visualize that a little
more clearly,
we can just draw that difference
or that error vector, which I
will start to call e,
along with it.
Now, it seems like, based on
this particular configuration of
u and v,
a negative value of k seems to
be pretty bad.
This error vector that we're
seeing drawn in dotted red here,
or dotted pink,
seems to be pretty long.
You would agree?
Same with over here.
It seems to be pretty long.
But right now, it seems to be
getting shorter and shorter and
shorter and shorter and shorter.
And somewhere around here, it
seems to be as short as can be.
And then it starts to extend
again.
So if you had to guess,
what property does this shortest
error vector satisfy?
Yeah, through.
There's a right angle.
Yeah, exactly.
The way to make this error
vector,
which is u minus kv,
as short as possible,
is to make it perpendicular to v
v and also kv, because v and kv
live on the same line.
Do we see that?
Good.
So our observation is that when
the error vector e,
which is my big vector,
well not big, but the vector u,
the one who I am trying to
approximate,
minus kv,
is orthogonal,
remember this is just a fancy
word for perpendicular, to v,
its length seems to be
minimized.
And so we're not ambiguous here.
Let's say e's length.
Are we convinced of that? This
is not a formal proof yet, but
at least based on this one
example, Well,
it seems like when this error
vector is perpendicular
to the vector we are using to
make our approximation,
then its length is as short as
possible.
Do we agree with that?
OK.
That's a good theory.
How do we prove that that is the
case?
I'm not going to walk through
the, I'm not going to write out
the entire argument here, but we
can make the argument to
convince you of why this is the
case.
Let me redraw this diagram here.
Pretend this is u,
this is v,
and why don't I put in green,
this is k,
and the corresponding error
vector in red,
Is there?
Why is the orthogonal error
vector or that is why is the
value of K that makes this error
vector orthogonal to V?
Why is this the shortest
possible error?
But how would you argue that no
other error vector could be
shorter
Yeah?
I guess because if you change k
to anything,
that line would become the
hypotenuse of a triangle.
And that's always longer than a
string.
Exactly, exactly, exactly.
Think of it this way.
Let's pretend you want to say,
no, no.
There is a different k whose
error vector is even shorter
than this orthogonal one.
You say, OK, bet.
Well then,
pretend this is the value of k I
pick,
like k prime v.
Now I can draw a right angle
triangle in here
where the length of your new
error vector is the hypotenuse
and the length of the orthogonal
error vector is not the
hypotenuse.
So its length has to be less
than the length of the
hypotenuse.
And that right angle triangle is
coming from the fact that we've
picked this error vector to be
orthogonal to v.
If you pick any other k,
you'll get a different error
vector.
And that error vector by this
argument
would be longer than the
orthogonal error vector.
Do you agree with that?
So our initial guess that the
orthogonal
error vector is the shortest
possible one is indeed true.
Orthogonal error vector is the
shortest.
Another way of putting it is
that it minimizes
the length of u minus kv
squared.
Or you don't need to square.
It minimizes the length of u
minus kv.
Now, there are two ways we are
going to actually find the value
of k that does this.
Right now, we know what the
optimal case should satisfy.
It should make u minus kv
orthogonal to v.
We don't know what that k
actually is yet.
There are two ways we could do
it.
One is to continue this
geometric argument, which we're
about to do.
But there's another way you
could find the best value of k,
the one that minimizes the
length of this error vector.
Using things that we did earlier
in the semester, like how else
do you think you could do this?
Find the k that minimizes the
length of this error vector.
Yeah,
Kate? In order orthogonal,
can't you use dot products,
like in C1,
dot products of e and v would be
0? That's what we're going to
do.
That is what we're going to do.
What I'm asking for you to do is
brainstorm another way we could
do it that doesn't involve using
the dot product.
Yeah.
You find the magnitude of the
derivative.
Yeah.
We can treat this as a function
of k.
Just imagine u and v are vectors
that are given to you.
You can treat them as constants.
You can think of this as a
function of just k and take its
derivative and set it equal to
0.
And when you solve for k,
you're going to get the exact
same thing we get when we use
the approach that we just heard,
which is that by setting the
error vector to be orthogonal to
v.
And both end up giving you the
same answer.
So we're about to do it the dot
product orthogonality way.
But if you look at homework
three more carefully now, one of
the questions has you do it the
derivative way.
So there,
this will be squared.
And one of the ideas you looked
at in homework one when you
looked at maximizing log of
something versus the original
function is that when you apply
an operation that doesn't change
the order of the inputs, then
the minimizer or maximizer is
still the same.
Because the length of a vector
can't be negative,
squaring the length of the
vector doesn't change which
vector is the shortest.
But it's easier to minimize the
squared length.
That's because you can write
this as the dot product of u
minus kv with u minus kv.
But if you don't have the
square, then you have a whole
square root in it, and that's
annoying to deal with.
Okay.
Anyways,
here,
we are going to do this the
geometric way.
Let me draw this picture once
again.
We want this error vector e,
which is u minus kv,
to be orthogonal
to v or kv?
I mean, v and kv, you know, if a
vector is orthogonal to one of
them, then it's orthogonal to
both of them.
So just to avoid injecting
additional variables into this
situation,
why don't we just say it should
be orthogonal to v?
Okay,
so Caitlyn, Can you remind us of
what you said we would do here?
Good and what should we set that
equal to?
Good
Is everyone clear on why we are
doing this?
We want this error vector
To be orthogonal to the vector
we are using to make our
approximation V
Now there's no K involved here.
Where does the K enter the
picture?
Yeah.
Good.
Now we have an expression that
involves a k, and we can solve
this for k.
And the expression is going to
involve u and v.
What do we do from here?
We can use the distributive
property of the dot product
to say that this is v dot u
minus v dot
kv.
That is 0.
What do we do now?
Again, my goal is to isolate for
K.
How do I keep moving?
You good? I can add this term to
both sides.
We will do that, but there's one
other thing I want to do first.
I want to try and isolate a
little more for k.
How can I do that?
Because right now, k is like in
this dot product.
Yeah, Alex? Can you divide
everything by v?
Good.
I'm glad you said that.
No, we cannot, because we can
divide both sides by a scalar.
But v is a vector.
Remember, this is a dot product
that involves v, and there's no
dot division.
There's a dot product, but not
the opposite of that.
Good.
But I'm glad you said that,
because that's an important
thing to clarify.
What else can we do?
Yeah, I'll do that.
Could we dot product the v and
the kv, and then that would
be two scalars, and we could
take k out of it?
Good.
The main idea I was getting at
here is that we can pull the k
out of this.
So as an aside here,
x dot product with 2y is the
same as 2 times the dot product
of x with y.
You can pull a scalar out of the
dot product.
So what that means here is that,
and just to make this look a
little more alphabetical,
I'm going to write this as u dot
v,
even though,
I mean,
we can do that because v dot u
and u dot v are the same thing.
Minus k times v dot v,
that's equal to 0.
Now we're almost there.
All I need to do is add one of
these terms to the other side.
I'll add k times v dot v.
That'll give me u dot v is equal
to k times v dot v.
And what does that tell me about
k?
If I divide both sides by v dot
v,
it tells me k is u dot v over v
dot v.
And now that this is the optimal
k, I'm going to call it k star.
This is what you'll see it being
called in the notes.
What this is telling me is the
optimal amount of v
to take if I want kv to be as
close
to u as possible.
So in this picture,
of which there is a cleaner
version in the notes,
this k star number is chosen
such that u minus k star v is
orthogonal to v.
And among all possible u minus
kv's,
this specific one is the
shortest possible.
Do we agree?
OK.
Now you may be wondering,
what is the purpose of this
approximation problem? Maybe I
should have started with that.
The short answer is that when we
eventually come back to the
linear regression problem,
Remember, the whole reason we
started to talk about linear
algebra is so that we could
eventually go back to linear
regression and learn how to use
multiple input variables or
multiple features.
This idea of approximating one
vector using one or more other
vectors is what the linear
regression problem boils down
to.
This is the simplest way we can
start to make that connection
clear.
Even if you look at the argument
I just made before in which
you're going to use calculus to
minimize this function,
it's not so different than the
things we were doing before.
You're minimizing something
squared.
You see where the similarities
are starting to come.
You can think of this as an
actual and this as a predicted.
It's not so different.
So this is the first building
block in that problem.
So now what I want you to do is
synthesize what we've just
discussed.
and use it in an activity.
So let's suppose u is the vector
1, 2,
2,
v is the vector 1, 1, 1.
The first thing I want you to do
is find what we will
call the orthogonal, I should
have defined this already,
but the orthogonal projection
of u
onto v.
And that is the vector
defined by taking that k star
amount of v that we just found.
which is u dot v over v dot v
times v, okay?
So I guess actually going back
to this picture,
this green vector,
we will call it p.
It's just a rebadged name for k
star v.
And p is called the orthogonal
projection of u onto v.
So that's the vector I want you
to find here.
I want you to find that optimal
amount,
k,
using this specific u and v,
and use that to find what the
orthogonal projection itself is.
Because k star just tells you
how much of v to take,
I want you to actually multiply
that by v and see what we end up
with.
And what I want you to do second
Find is find the error vector,
which is E,
which is the difference between
the vector we are projecting
or starting with,
U,
and the projection itself, which
is k star v,
which is also p.
And what is it orthogonal to?
That's what I want you to
discuss.
So I've given you a specific u,
a specific v.
Apply the formula we developed
moments ago to this specific
situation.
That formula would tell us how
much of v to take to get as
close to u as possible if we're
forced to travel in the
direction of v.
and then figure out how far that
projection is from you.
Question?
Oh,
that's not a division.
Sorry,
I can make that more clear.
No, that's a good clarification.
I was just saying this thing is
also called P.
OK,
thank you.
Thank you for clarifying.
Thank you.
Discuss with the people near
you.
I'll give you a few moments to
work on this.
I'm going to take a picture of
this.
This is the error under the
operables.
The operable error.
What is it?
The arachnoid? The arachnoid?
It's a card.
Right,
right, right.
It's a card with a D.
You get the thought product.
Oh, it's a long night.
It's a bad fraction.
It's a good one.
I can grab it.
One, two,
three, four, five, six,
seven, eight,
nine, 10,
It's okay, it's just as close to
the L on the other side as
possible.
I think so, yeah.
Everything in variables is a
little flat.
I think,
I say tongue notation.
It's a vector.
Because I have a higher chance
of getting the algebra right
than the previous class.
The division as well.
the thing I used to post in two
or three finals.
Okay, we can start taking this
up.
So again, this is our u,
which in this question we tell
you is 122.
And this is our v.
It's not exactly drawn to scale,
which in this question we tell
you is 1, 1, 1.
What is k star here, and how did
you find that? And remember, k
star is the amount of v you need
to take.
How did you find that?
Sure.
I did u dot v over v dot v.
Good.
And what were both of those
here?
So u dot v would be 1 plus 2
plus 2, which equals 5.
Good.
And then 1 plus 1 plus 1, which
equals 3.
So k star, this is telling us
how much of v we need to take to
make this approximation that is
as close to u as possible.
The new term is that the
approximation itself, which is a
vector that comes from taking k
star v,
this is called the orthogonal
projection
of u onto v.
So here that vector is
five-thirds v,
which is just the vector
five-thirds,
and five-thirds.
So in this picture, that would
be something like
this.
One reason this is called the
orthogonal projection,
or well, the reason it is called
the orthogonal projection is
because,
as we've derived,
the error is orthogonal to the
thing we are projecting onto.
So here u is the vector being
projected,
v is the vector we're projecting
onto,
but the mental model I want you
to have is that like this
orthogonal projection p here is
like the shadow of u onto v.
So imagine we had the Sun and
we started shining light
from here.
Okay,
p is where the shadow would
live.
It wouldn't go past P.
It wouldn't go less than that.
P is where the shadow would be.
Do you kind of see that?
Yeah.
So I thought the projection was
the word for the scalar
coefficient.
No.
The projection is the word for
the vector itself.
So a projection of one vector is
just another vector that's
extended onto that one? Correct.
It could be shorter, but yeah.
Yes.
So that's an important
clarification.
projection,
the orthogonal projection is the
term for the vector itself.
Good.
Yes.
Is there a book cap term for k
then?
Not quite.
No.
No, the optimal amount or
something like that, yeah.
Good.
Yeah.
One more thing.
For the error vector,
can we always assume that that's
the optimal k?
It depends on the question.
Maybe a question would ask you
about the error if you use a
different value of k to compare
it or something.
But given no other information,
yeah.
Similar to when we ask you
questions about the simple
linear regression line.
Usually there's a sentence
saying,
assume we found this line by
minimizing mean squared error,
meaning it's asking about the
optimal line, not some random
one.
Good.
Then we told you to find that
error vector,
which in this picture, I'll use
a different color for, because
red meant something else here.
What is the error vector here?
What are its components? Let's
see.
Zero.
Yeah,
Alex.
Sure.
I got a negative 2 thirds,
1 third, 1 third.
Negative 2 thirds,
1 third, and 1 third.
Remember, the error is coming
from subtracting u with p,
not u with v,
right?
This came from u minus the
projection, which is the same as
u minus k star v.
Now,
what vector is this error vector
orthogonal to?
There's two on the screen that
it's orthogonal to, and one that
it is definitely not.
What is it not orthogonal to?
Yeah,
u.
It's not orthogonal to u.
We can see in this picture, u
and e are not orthogonal.
What is the error vector
orthogonal to?
V.
What's another quirk about this
error vector that you might like
jumps out to you maybe?
Other than that, it involves
fractions.
Something interesting about it.
Yeah? It adds up to 0.
It adds up to 0.
Why is that?
Why does it add up to 0?
And is that always guaranteed to
be the case?
Yeah, it's because remember the
defining characteristic of this
error vector is that it's
orthogonal to V
meaning whatever the error
vector was going to be when you
dot product did it with V v,
that would be 0.
But v is just 1, 1, 1.
And any time you dot a vector
with 1, 1, 1,
all you end up doing is just
adding up the components of the
other vector.
Think of any vector you want,
245, 245.
Dot that with 1, 1, 1.
What do you get? You just get 2
plus 4 plus 5.
What that tells you is the
components of the error
need to add up to 0.
And now that would be true even
if this was 2, 2, 2, for
example,
because then you would just be
multiplying 2 times the first
thing plus 2 times the second
thing plus two times the third
thing,
that being zero would be the
same as the first plus the
second plus the third add up to
zero.
This idea of dot producting one
vector
with a vector of all ones is
actually going to come up quite
a bit this semester.
So recognizing that dot
producting with a vector of all
ones gives you the sum of the
other vector is important.
And in fact,
in the lecture attendance form,
the most common question was,
like, would I think of what
vectors to use for the
Cauchy-Schwarz inequality?
That's like what basically
everybody thought.
And like I said,
you'll sort of learn to see the
patterns as you work on some of
these questions.
But like one of the tricks in
the Cauchy-Schwarz inequality
type questions is often one of
the two vectors is a vector of
all ones.
Because that allows you to get
the sum of the vectors,
the other vectors things.
So that was sort of an aside
here.
OK.
OK,
a final example I want us to
look at,
which will lead nicely into the
lab exercise tomorrow,
is let's suppose we have the
vectors u, which is 3, 5,
v1,
which is 6, negative 2,
and v2, which is 1, 3.
Let me draw a picture of all of
these creatures.
V1 is going to live somewhere
down here.
V2 is going to live up here.
And U is going to live somewhere
over there.
OK,
task,
write u
as a linear
combination
of
v1 and v2.
This seems like it's got nothing
to do with what we were just
discussing about orthogonal
projections.
And indeed,
I could have asked this question
last time,
maybe even the lecture before
that.
Writing one vector as a linear
combination of others
is like, that's a problem we are
going to study quite a bit and
the reason we will study it is
because essentially our linear
regression problem boils down to
being able to do this optimally,
OK,
when some linear combinations
can't be made exactly.
We will cover that in a little
bit.
What I want you to do is for
now,
just see if you can solve this.
Write u as a linear combination
of v1 and v2.
We looked at examples of this
before.
You set up a system of equations
and solve.
But as you will see, there's
actually another way you can do
it.
It's going to be a B now, and 2
equals 2.
Good
afternoon.
Good afternoon.
Good
afternoon.
This one is just being used in
the workshop.
The workshop establishes the
rest of these.
I know it's very common.
How much is a year?
I think a year is fine.
All right, that's okay.
It's definitely rational,
but I don't think it's good.
Okay, let's do it.
What do we do?
Are we done?
I think it says RDSS.
RDSS, RDSS,
RDSS, RDSS, RDSS, RDSS,
RDSS,
RDSS, RDSS.
It's awesome.
Okay,
29.
Bro.
Thankful formulation.
So I won't provide this long
term.
I'll like it.
It will take 280, like,
yeah.
Please.
I don't know, what did I do
wrong?
I don't know,
it's like.
Nine, nine, nine, nine, nine.
Okay, sounds like I hear people
having worked on it.
Are these the numbers you got? B
is nine fifths and A is one
fifth?
Okay.
So, we know how to solve this
problem.
We didn't need anything from
today's lecture to do that.
But we just, we did it the hard
way.
But there is actually an easier
way of staring at us in the face
if you paid close attention into
this picture.
And let me make that clear here,
the
hard and annoying way.
Nobody likes doing this.
What was the easier way?
Go first.
First, what do you notice about
v1 and v2?
The orthogonal.
OK, the dot product of u and v
is 0.
OK,
what does that mean?
What if I wanted to try and use
things we learned about today,
about orthogonal projections?
Even though that's not really
what the question asks us to do.
How does that apply?
We could decompose, like,
the v vectors on each of the v
vectors.
Yeah, if you look at this, this
just seems like a rotated
version of the x-axis and
y-axis.
What does that mean?
Well,
let's suppose, this is not what
the question asked me to do,
but let's suppose I find the
projection.
By the way, when we say
projection, we just mean
orthogonal projection.
Why don't I find the projection
of u onto v1?
Where is that going to get me?
That's going to get me to like
here.
This would be the vector p.
What would the error be?
The error is going to be
orthogonal to my projection.
It's going to look like that.
But what do you notice about
this error vector?
What did you notice?
It's parallel to v2.
So everything I can't make by
projecting onto v1,
I can make by projecting onto
v2.
And vice versa.
Like v1, v2, those are just
arbitrary names.
I could have projected onto v2
first.
That would have gotten me up
till here.
What's my error? It's this.
And how do I get that? I get
that by projecting onto v1.
So what we're seeing here is
that when you're starting with
vectors that are orthogonal,
Well,
writing another vector as a
linear combination of them
is actually very easy, because
you can do it just by projecting
onto those orthogonal vectors.
Here's another way to look at
it.
And you're going to practice
this in lab tomorrow,
the easier way.
Notice,
v1 and v2 are orthogonal.
So suppose
it is possible to say u is equal
to a times v1 plus b times v2.
I'll make this really quick.
What would happen if I took the
dot product of both sides with
v1?
Legal operation.
I have a vector on the left, a
vector on the right.
What would happen if I did that?
What do I get on the left when I
do that?
u dot v1.
And what do I get on the right?
I have a times v1 dot v1 plus b
times v2 dot v1.
But what do you know about v2
dot v1?
Zero.
Goodbye.
Okay, gone.
And now,
all we're left with is something
that looks suspiciously
familiar.
You divide both sides here by v1
dot v1,
and this just tells you the
coefficient on a
is u dot v1 over v1 dot v1,
which is the optimal scalar
amount of v1 you take when you
project u onto v1.
So what this is telling us is
whenever we're asked to find one
vector as a linear combination
of some building blocks, if
those building blocks are
orthogonal, you can avoid the
annoyingness of having to solve
systems of equations by just
projecting individually onto
each of the vectors, which is
why,
moving forward, we're going to
spend a lot of time thinking
about orthogonal building
blocks, because they're very
easy to work with in this
setting.
OK?
And I encourage you,
obviously we're out of time
here, but I have office hours
after.
I encourage you to just find u
dot v1 over v1 dot v1.
And if you do it, you'll find
out that it's a fifth.
v1 dot v1 is 40.
u dot v1 is 18 minus 10, which
is 8.
8 over 40 is 1 over 5.
So it works out.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah,
yeah.
It was minus 2.
V1 is 6 minus 2.
So there's a minus 2 there.
That's a minus 2.
Yeah.
I think that's one way to think
about it, yeah.
Okay.
I mean, you can just go to a
different lab.
Oh,
I see.
Oh, I see.
Well,
good luck with that.
Nope.
You probably won't get in the
habit of posting before but you
can come to office hours on on
Thursday or Friday of the year.
Where's the interview?
Open it.
It's all there.
Yeah, that is what I think.
JP Morgan.
Those are too hot.
They say it will just take time.
The semester don't ever get
boring, so I got it.
Because apparently,
like, if you start moving them.
Physics 2 on top.
Like, I've already done the
homework, so you see it, add
your.
It's basically perfect.
Break this down.
Yeah.
Yeah, we'll go to a couple more
places, then.
Wait, so you don't have to flex
your phone, then.
I don't.
He's always going to do a lot of
work today.
Well,
well,
well.
There's a number for...
DR, right?
Yeah, how are you?
I want to finish T-81.
That's fair.
Maybe let's step outside because
there's another cluster.
Figure out a memory grab.
We could see you after that.